Guide to the Vita Sackville-West Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Vita Sackville-West papers
1897-2003
1900-1960
GEN MSS 925
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
12.84
(19 boxes)
The collection consists chiefly of correspondence, diaries, notebooks, scrapbooks, business and estate records, writings, lectures, and gardening papers. Correspondents include family members such as Lionel Edward Sackville-West, Victoria Sackville, Harold Nicolson, and Nigel Nicolson, and friends and lovers including Rosamund Grosvenor, Hilda Matheson, Gwen St. Aubyn, and Christopher St. John. Writings include typescripts and manuscripts for works including the novels The Edwardians and All Passion Spent. Gardening papers include horticultural catalogs, files on the National Trust's garden committee, and research materials. The collection documents Vita Sackville-West's family life, love affairs with women including Christopher St. John and Gwen St. Aubyn, her literary life and circle, including both Sackville-West's work and that of friends including Virginia Woolf, and the management of the Sissinghurst Castle estate and gardens.
Sackville-West, V. (Victoria), 1892-1962
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Bernard Quaritch, Ltd. on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, the Frederick W. Hilles Fund, and the Hubert Amer McGuire Memorial Fund, 2012.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Vita Sackville-West
Vita (Victoria) Sackville-West (1892-1962), was an English author, poet and gardener. She was the daughter of Lionel Sackville-West, 3rd Baron Sackville, and Victoria Sackville-West. She and her husband Sir Harold Nicolson created the gardens at their Sissinghurst Castle estate.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists chiefly of correspondence, diaries, notebooks, scrapbooks, business and estate records, writings, lectures, and gardening papers. Correspondents include family members such as Lionel Edward Sackville-West, Victoria Sackville, Harold Nicolson, and Nigel Nicolson, and friends and lovers including Rosamund Grosvenor, Hilda Matheson, Gwen St. Aubyn, and Christopher St. John. Writings include typescripts and manuscripts for works including the novels The Edwardians and All Passion Spent. Gardening papers include horticultural catalogs, files on the National Trust's garden committee, and research materials. The collection documents Vita Sackville-West's family life, love affairs with women including Christopher St. John and Gwen St. Aubyn, her literary life and circle, including both Sackville-West's work and that of friends including Virginia Woolf, and the management of the Sissinghurst Castle estate and gardens.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1897-2003. II. Personal Papers, 1900s-1960s. III. Writings and Lectures, 1920s-1990s. IV. Gardening Papers, 1930s-1960s.
Related Materials
Harold Nicolson Papers (GEN MSS 614). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Authors, English -- 20th Century -- Archives; Gardening -- England; Lesbian authors -- England; Lesbians -- England; Women authors; Sissinghurst Castle (England); Diaries -- England -- 20th Century; LGBTQ resource; Nicolson, Harold, 1886-1968; Nicolson, Nigel, 1917-2004; Grosvenor, Rosamund, 1888-1944; Matheson, Hilda, 1888-1940; Sackville, Lionel Edward Sackville-West, Baron, 1867-1928; Sackville-West, V. (Victoria), 1892-1962; Sackville, Victoria Josephine Sackville-West, Lady, 1862-1936; St. Aubyn, Gwen; St. John, Christopher (Christopher Marie); Woolf, Virginia, 1882-1941
- Correspondence, 1897-2003; Series I; 4 linear feet (4 boxes)
  - Correspondence to and from Vita Sackville-West, 1909-1961 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes incoming correspondence from Rosamund Grosvenor, Vita's mother Lady Sackville, Miss Macmillan, Hilda Matheson, and others. Outgoing correspondence includes letters from Vita to Lady Sackville and others, as well as copies of letters to Rosamund Grosvenor. Also includes correspondence documenting the sale of furniture.
  - Correspondence from others, 1910-1960 (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence from Pat Dansey, Sybil Colefax, Cyril Connolly, Ruth Draper, Rosamund Grosvenor, Eardley Knollys, Lord Lascelles, and others.
  - Correspondence from others, 1904-1957 (Box 3)
    Includes correspondence from Harold Nicolson, Benedict Nicolson, Nigel Nicolson, Lady Powerscourt, Lady Sackville, Lord (Lionel) Sackville, Gwen St. Aubyn, Christopher St. John, and others, including letters to Vita Sackville-West regarding her mother Lady Sackville. Also includes letters to Lady Sackville from Geoffrey Scott and Lord Sackville.
  - Correspondence from others, 1897-2003 (Box 4)
    Includes correspondence to Vita Sackville-West from Margaret Voigt, Mrs. Wilton, Laura James, the staff of the Queen Mother, and others, as well as assorted family correspondence, including condolence letters following the death of Lord Sackville. Also includes photographs of Hilda Matheson, excerpts from correspondence with Margaret Howard, and Nigel Nicolson correspondence and other papers related to his biographical writings.
- Personal papers, 1900s-1960s; Series II; 4.42 linear feet (9 boxes)
  - Diaries and notebooks, 1950-1962 (Box 5)
    Includes travel diaries, daybooks, and gardening notebooks. Also contains news clippings and Christopher St. John's "horrifying document," a manuscript notebook detailing the end of her affair with Sackville-West in 1933.
  - Diaries and notebooks, 1900s-1960s (Box 6)
    Includes travel diaries, daybooks, and gardening notebooks. Also contains at least one datebook kept by Lady Sackville.
  - Diaries and notebooks, 1931-1955 (Box 7)
  - Estate mananagment and financial records, 1930s-1960s (Box 8)
    Financial statements and correspondence documenting the managment of the Sissinghurst Castle estate, personal property, and Lady Sackville's death.
  - Scrapbooks, 1920s-1930s (Box 9)
    Includes news clippings covering Vita Sackville-West's publications and one scrapbook with clippings about Virginia Woolf.
  - Scrapbook, 1919-1922 (Box 10 (Oversize))
    Includes news clippings relating to Heritage, The Dragon in Shallow Waters, Orchard and Vinyard, Grand Canyon, The Eagle and the Dove, and other publications.
  - Scrapbooks, 1929-1935 (Box 11 (Oversize))
    Includes clippings from The Edwardians, All Passions Spent, The Dark Island, and other publications.
  - Scrapbook, 1938-1941 (Box 12 (Oversize))
    Includes clippings from "Country Notes" for the New Statesman.
  - Honors and business papers, 1940s-1960s (Box 13)
    Documentation of honors and distinctions awarded Vita Sackville-West, with correspondence. Also includes records of a loan to her son Nigel Nicolson's publishing company.
- Writings and lectures, 1920s-1990s; Series III; 3.42 linear feet (5 boxes)
  - Typescripts, manuscripts, clippings, and correspondence, 1920s-1960s (Box 14)
    Material from The Edwardians, Faces: Profiles of Dogs, The Eagle and the Dove, All Passion Spent, The Easter Party, and other publications; notes from national broadcast talks.
  - Typescripts, manuscripts, clippings, and correspondence, 1920s-1960s (Box 15)
    Material from Family History, The Grand Canyon, Passenger to Tehran, Nursery Rhymes and other publications; also includes material from "The Metaphysical School", "Is it Still a Disadvantage to be a Woman" lectures and other talks and lectures.
  - Typscripts, manuscripts, notes, and correspondence, 1920s-1960s (Box 16)
    Mostly material from lectures, talks and presentations given in person and on radio throughout the UK and Europe.
  - Business correspondence relating to publishing and royalties, 1930s-1950s (Box 17)
  - Writings by others about Vita Sackville-West, 1990s (Box 18)
- Gardening papers, 1930s-1960s; Series IV; 1; (1 box) (Box 19)
  Horticultural catalogs, files on The National Trust's garden committee, gardening research and material on ornamental fauna.
- March 2018 Acquisition, 1916-1961